本劇改編自聖經  將始終盡力保持《聖經》真諦
某些場景含暴力鏡頭  請觀眾自行斟酌
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
起初
In the beginning,
上帝創造天地
God created the heavens and the earth.
亞當和夏娃違背了上帝的旨意偷食了禁果
Adam and Eve disobeyed God and ate the forbidden fruit.
從那之後  因為該隱殺了亞伯
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
上帝目睹了人類內心深處太多的惡念
God has seen too much evil in human hearts.
上帝警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
亞伯拉罕
Abraham.
上帝對我說話了
God has spoken to me.
他將指引我們去新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
他保證我的後裔會多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
你會有孩子的   我不會有
You will have a child. I can't.
我的年紀太大了
It's too late for me.
亞伯拉罕  土地不夠   我們人太多了
Abraham, there just isn't enough land. There are too many of us.
是時候分道揚鑣了
It's time we go our separate ways.
發生了什麼事   他們人太多了
- What happened? - There were so many of them.
羅得呢   還活著   但被抓走了
- And Lot? - Alive. But taken prisoner.
如果我連自己的家人都領導不了  又如何去領導一個民族呢
How can I lead a people when I can't even lead my own family?
相信上帝
Trust in God!
亞伯拉罕   我們還是要去所多瑪
Abraham, we're carrying on to Sodom.
你們要毀滅它嗎   整座城市
You're going to destroy it. The whole city?
殲滅惡人的同時也要消滅那些好人嗎
Will you destroy the good men along with the evil ones?
亞伯拉罕  你的妻子在哪兒
Abraham, where is your wife?
雖然她老了  撒拉會生下一個男孩
Though she is barren, Sarah will have a son.
要給他起名叫做以撒
You will name him Isaac.
上帝要你去獻祭
God wants a sacrifice.
你還不相信我的忠誠嗎
Have I not shown you enough faith?
亞伯拉罕
Abraham!
《聖經》
第02集-出埃及記
經過近400年的亞伯拉罕
Nearly 400 years after Abraham,
飢荒迫使以色列人遠離應許之地  來到埃及
famine has forced the Israelites from the promised land to Egypt.
在那裡  他們成為了法老的奴隸
Here they've been enslaved by Pharaoh.
亞伯拉罕和上帝成了遙遠的記憶
Abraham and God have become a distant memory.
他的子民都淪為役畜
All his people reduced to beasts of burden,
只有一人幸免於難
except one.
摩西
Moses.
你不能再去爭強斗勇了   我無法拒絕
- You're not going to fight again. - I can't refuse.
母親  他是法老的兒子
He's Pharaohs son, Mother.
他們之間的較量必須停止
The fighting between them has to stop.
摩西並不想去   是你兒子逼他的  屢敗屢戰
Moses doesn't want to fight. It's your son who forces him into it and keeps losing.
也許你是我姐姐的心頭寶
You may be my sister's favourite,
但我才是未來的法老
but I will be Pharaoh.
我會是埃及的神
I will be god!
別打了   還手  我命令你
- Please. - Fight me! I order you!
摩西
Moses.
夠了
Enough!
啊
Ahh!
他得明白自己的身份   是你先開始的
- He needs to learn his place. - You were the one that started...
我是未來的法老王
I will be Pharaoh!
那麼你的行為處事最好有個法老王的樣子
Then you better start behaving like one.
都是你的錯  你就不該讓姐姐撫養他
This is your fault. You should never have let her keep him.
閉嘴
Silence.
你根本不是我族人
You're not one of us.
我叫你閉嘴   他在說什麼
Silence, I said! What's he talking about?
你最好現在就告訴他
You'd better tell him now.
你
You!
跟我過來
Come with me!
母親  告訴我什麼
Mother, tell me what?
什麼啊
What?
摩西   我把你當兒子一樣疼愛
Moses, I love you like a son.
但是你並非我親生
But you're not my blood.
你是奴隸之子
You were born a slave.
把他們都抓來
Take them all!
我父親殺了很多孩子
Father killed so many children.
他擔心會有叛亂
He feared a rebellion.
你的族人數量太多了
Your people were too many.
我的   人民
My... - People?
我救了你
I saved you.
你的人民就在外面  摩西
Your people are out there, Moses.
我們的奴隸
Our slaves.
那些以色列人
The Israelites.
你有個哥哥  叫亞倫
You had a brother- Aaron.
還有一個姐姐   叫米利暗
And a sister- Miriam.
但他們跟我們不一樣
But they are not like us.
快點  你  快點
Come on! You! Move along!
快點  快起來  婊子
Come on! You'll get more!
他們崇拜亞伯拉罕的神
They worship the God of Abraham.
而祂拋棄了他們
And he has deserted them.
起來   停
Get up! Stop.
以色列賤民
Israelite scum!
不要  求求你  我求你了
No, please! Please, I beg of you!
狗奴才
Dog!
快跑  快跑
Run. Run.
我會把屍體藏起來
I will hide the body.
主人  這是摩西的護身符
My lord, the amulet of Moses.
要不要追捕他   不
Shall we hunt him down? No.
讓他走   他已經不會造成威脅了
Let him go. He's no threat now.
歡迎進入你的新生活  摩西
Welcome to your new life, Moses!
你現在什麼都不是了
You are nothing now!
什麼都不是
Nothing.
你的子民都在外面呢  摩西
Your people are out there, Moses.
你非我族人
You're not one of us.
他們崇拜亞伯拉罕的神
They worship the God of Abraham.
你不應該讓她收留他
You should never have let' her keep him.
祂拋棄了他們
And he has deserted them.
我會成為法老
I will be Pharaoh!
摩西
Moses.
我在這
I am here.
我是亞伯拉罕  以撒和雅各的神
I am the God of Abraham, of Isaac and Jacob.
你是真實存在的嗎   是的
You are real? I am.
我看到我的子民所受的痛苦
I have seen the misery of my people.
我派你到法老那裡去   帶他們離開埃及
I am sending you to Pharaoh to bring them out of Egypt.
但是我要怎麼做才能讓他們自由
But how can I set them free?
我現在不是一個王子
I'm not a prince now.
我什麼都不是
I'm nothing.
我會與你同在
I will be with you.
有了你的力量
With your power,
我會讓我的人民獲得自由
I will set my people free.
在埃及  新王已經登基
In Egypt, there is a new man on the throne.
摩西的老對手已經成了法老王
Moses' old rival is now Pharaoh.
謝謝你  父親
Thank you, Father.
終有一天  你會擁有一支軍隊   真正的軍隊
One day you will have an army of them. Real ones.
快幹活   快幹活
- Come on! - Come on!
一切如昨
Nothing has changed.
仍舊水深火熱
So much suffering. Please!
你   你
Hey, Wu! Hey, you!
回去幹活
Back to work!
繼續  幹活
Go on! Move it!
等等  請等等
Wait. Wait. Please.
我來跟他說  大人
I'll take care of him, master.
你在幹什麼  想讓我們都挨打嗎
What are you doing? Trying to get us all a beating?
你是誰
Who are you?
你在這幹什麼   我是摩西
What are you doing here? My name is Moses.
摩西
Moses.
你就是摩西
You are Moses?
我要見你們的長老
I need to see your elders.
跟我來
Come with me.
這人說他是摩西
This man says he's Moses!
那個逃跑的王子
The Runaway Prince.
你因犯謀殺罪被通緝
You're wanted for murder.
如果你真是他  為什麼回來
If you're who you say you are, why would you return?
上帝派我回來的
God has sent me.
我到這兒來
I am here
給你們自由
to set you free.
上帝派你來的
God has sent you?
沒錯
Yes. God...
上帝派我來  向你們傳話
sent me to speak to you.
你們還記得上帝嗎
Have you forgotten God?
即使你們忘記了他
Even if you have...
他卻未曾忘記你們
He has not forgotten you.
恐怕你忘記了
In case you had forgotten,
法老才是我們唯一讓我們害怕的神
Pharaoh is the only god we have to fear.
你認為他會輕易放我們走嗎
And you think he's just going to let us go?
是誰創造了大地
Who created the earth,
海洋
sea,
天空
the sky?
是誰創造了你們
Who created you?
法老王
Pharaoh?
還是上帝
Or God?
你瘋了  不
You're demented. No.
他沒有
He isn't.
他是我的弟弟
He's my brother
亞倫
Aaron.
摩西
Moses!
上帝向我托夢
God sent me a dream...
說你會回來
to say you would return.
這是米利暗  你的姐姐
This is Miriam, your sister.
弟弟
Brother.
這是我的孩子
My children.
我的家人
My family.
我的子民
My people
我們的子民
Our people.
-上帝的子民  -上帝的子民
- God's people! - God's people!
老法老王或許喜歡你
Old Pharaoh may have been fond of you,
但你現在要對付的是他的兒子
But it's his son you'll have to deal with now.
法老為什麼要見你
Why would Pharaoh even see you?
Oh.
他會想見我的
He'll want to see me.
你有兒子
You have a son.
有繼承人了
An heir.
我們的王朝將千秋萬代
Our dynasty will last forever.
你到這兒來做什麼  摩西
Why are you here, Moses?
來請求寬恕嗎
Have you come to ask for forgiveness?
不
No.
上帝出於某種目的救了我
God saved me for a purpose.
是嗎
Yes?
我是來要求你還他的子民自由的
I come to demand that you release his people from slavery.
要求
Demand?
讓我的子民離開
Let my people go.
你一直是名鬥士  摩西
You always were a fighter, Moses.
但你戰敗時從不自知
But you never knew when you were beaten.
倘若藐視上帝
If you defy God,
你會受到懲罰
you will be punished.
這麼多年後  你回來就為了威脅我嗎
You return, after all these years, to threaten me?
告訴我  是你那看不見的上帝要懲罰我嗎
Tell me. Is it your invisible God that's going to punish me?
那個拋棄他子民
The one who abandons his people?
逃避責任
The one who runs from his responsibilities?
逃避過去
From his past?
逃避家人的上帝
From his family?
告訴他們誰才是上帝
Teach them who God is.
我就是上帝
I am God!
摩西
Moses.
你惹怒了法老  他會懲罰我們的  懸崖勒馬吧
You've made Pharaoh angry. He will punish us. Don't make it worse.
上帝和我說過  倘若別無他法  他會迫使法老
God has spoken to me. He will force Pharaoh to free us.
還我們自由的
If he has to.
我們該怎麼辦  姐姐  哥哥
What should we do? Sister, Brother,
你們所有人
All of you.
相信上帝
Trust in God!
法老就在那兒
Pharaoh is over there.
你在殿上面見他的時候  他都充耳不聞  現在又怎麼會聽你的呢
If he didn't listen to you when you were six feet away, why would he hear you now?
到時候就知道了
You will see.
把你的木杖放進河裡
Put your staff to the water.
快  主人
Come, master!
快上來  血
Come out of the water! It's blood!
有血
It's blood!
到處都是血
It's blood everywhere!
血流成河了
The whole river!
主人
Master!
你不是上帝
You are not a god.
你只是凡人
You are just a man.
你一定會釋放我的子民
And you will set my people free.
走開
Move away!
摩西
Master.
Moses!
你相信了嗎  約書亞
Do you doubt, Joshua?
我這一生都被法老奴役
All my life, I have been Pharaohs.
我再也不會是個奴隸了
I will never be a slave again.
上帝與我們同在
God is with us.
這只是個開始
This is just the beginning.
上帝安排了十次災難來改變法老的想法
Our Lord is sending 10 plagues to change Pharaohs mind.
釋放我的子民
Let my people go.
不
No!
蝗蟲
Locusts.
快離開那  主人
Come away! Master!
不
No!
摩西  法老怎麼說  他應該醒悟過來了吧
Moses, what is Pharaohs answer? Surely he will see sense now.
不
No.
他還是不願意  還是這樣
He refuses. Again?
放棄吧  摩西  不然一切都來不及了
Give up, Moses, before it's too late.
災難不會停止的   除非法老王就範
God will keep on doing this until Pharaoh breaks.
怎麼了
What's wrong?
不久  最後一個瘟疫就會發生
Soon there will be a final plague.
死亡天使會降臨
The Angel of Death is coming.
所有長子都會死
Every first-born son will die.
不要啊
No.
不會發生在我們身上吧
But not us.
為什麼要懲罰我們
Why would he punish us?
死亡是衝著所有人來的
Death is coming for us all.
為什麼是我們
Why us?
同胞們
Friends!
只有我們謹遵上帝的指示
We can be spared God's vengeance,
才能逃過這一劫難
but only if we do exactly as he tells us.
別灑了
Don't spill.
每家每戶都要用血做記號
Every single house must be marked with blood.
以色列人拿羊血在門上做記號
The Israelites paint'lamb is blood on their doorways,
以表明自己是上帝的子民
identifying them as God's people.
上帝保佑我們
God will watch over us.
我們答應上帝要拯救我們的子民
We promised God would free our people.
但上帝卻送來了死亡
But now he sends us death.
我們必須相信他
We must trust in him.
來了
It's coming.
我們會有事嗎  -別怕  孩子
Will we be safe? Don't be afraid, my son.
父親   上帝保佑
Father, I'm-God have mercy.
法老王一意孤行
Pharaoh has not listened.
現在他的子民要替他承受這一切苦果
Whatever happens to his people is now on his head.
曾經我把他們視為我的同胞  約書亞
Once I counted them as my people, Joshua.
我們的自由是有代價的
Our freedom comes at a price.
死亡天使
The Angel of Death...
發現每戶以色列人家都用鮮血做了標記
finds every Israelite house painted with blood...
就放過了他們
and passes over.
為什麼
Why?
為什麼以色列奴隸還活著
Why should Israelite slaves have life...
而我兒子卻死了
when my son is dead?
起來
Get up.
滾  帶著你們那卑鄙的上帝
Go! And leave my land!
滾出我的國土
And take your wretched God with you!
東西都裝好  準備走了
Pack up. Get ready.
快來  走吧
Come on. Good.
摩西
Moses!
摩西  摩西
Moses! Moses!
你贏了
You won!
摩西
Moses!
他們做到了
They did it!
我們要去完成亞伯拉罕與上帝的聖約
We are going to fulfil Abraham's covenant with God.
去應許之地繁衍生息
We're going to live in the promised land...
擁有如繁星之多的後裔
with descendants as numerous as the stars.
我的孩子
My son.
奴隸怎可如此殘忍
How could slaves do this?
我在此向你發誓
I vow to you, here and now,
我會把以色列人抓回來
that I will bring the Israelites back...
讓他們為你建造世界上最宏偉的陵墓
and make them build you the greatest tomb the world has ever seen.
用摩西的屍體
Moses' body...
給陵墓奠基  給你陪葬
shall be buried in its foundations.
我還是不敢相信法老就這麼放了我們
I still can't believe Pharaoh just let us leave.
他的確這樣做了  -這是上帝的旨意
But he did. It's what God demanded.
經過這麼多事  只有瘋子才會再次觸怒上帝
Only a madman would defy God again after what he's done.
弟弟  接下來怎麼辦
Brother, what now?
弟弟
Brother?
上帝會指引我們
God will provide a way.
摩西  為什麼帶我們來這
Moses, why have you brought us here?
是上帝帶我們來的
God brought us here.
那上帝有沒有說怎麼過去
And what does God say about getting across?
埃及人  在山上
Egyptians. On the hill.
你的上帝現在在哪啊  摩西
Where is your God now, Moses?
追到他們了  他們被困了
We have them! They're trapped!
在那裡
There!
摩西
Moses!
戰車
Chariots!
他們追來了
They're here.
埃及人追來了
The Egyptians.
傻瓜  現在怎麼辦啊
Fool! What do we do now?
是不是因為埃及沒我們的葬身之地  所以你帶我們來這送死
Was it because there were no graves in Egypt that you brought us here to die?
看看你幹的好事
Because that is what you've done.
他們來了  怎麼辦  我們去哪裡
They're coming! What do we do? Where shall we go?
怎麼辦
Well?
摩西
Moses.
駕  駕  駕
Hyah! Hyah! Hyah!
把東西都放到車上
Get everything into the carts!
我的孩子
My children!
摩西  -摩西
Moses! Moses! Moses!
等待
Wait!
耶和華  我不相信這是你給我們安排的結局
Lord, I cannot believe this is the end you planned for us.
我們看著你降災給我們的仇敵
We have watched you bring terror on our enemies.
在那裡
There!
將死亡隔絕在我們的門外
You kept death from our door.
摩西  摩西  摩西
Moses! Moses! Moses!
主啊
Lord!
上帝與我們同在
God is with us!
跟我走
Follow me!
上帝與我們同在   我們從這直接過去
- God is with us! - We're gonna go straight through there.
把大家集中到一起
Get your men together!
快點  快點  咱們得馬上離開
- Hurry! Hurry! - We have to leave now!
快點燃火炬
Light torches! Quickly!
快跑  快跑
Let's go! Move it! Let's go!
快點  快點
Quickly! Hurry!
快點
Come on!
要有信心
Have faith!
快點
Come on!
別停下
Keep moving!
快
Hurry!
別怕  要有信心
Don't be afraid! Have faith!
快跑
Come on!
快跑   別停下來
Come on! Keep going!
等等
Wait!
給我追
After them!
快
NOW!
給我活捉摩西
Bring me Moses!
快跑
Run!
摩西  快跑
Moses! Come on!
接著跑
Keep moving!
快點
Hurry!
我看到他們的火炬了
I see their torches!
快跑  別停下
Come on! Keep moving!
嗯
On!
他們來了
They're coming.
They're coming!
快點
Hurry!
快跑
Run!
快啊
Hurry!
馬上就要到了
We're there!
加油
Come on!
加油   老爸
Come on, old man!
快點
Hurry!
我們到了
We're here!
他們還在追
They're still coming!
在那裡  那裡
There! Up there!
我們已經要抓到他們了
We've got them!
法老  你不是神
You are not a god, Pharaoh.
世上只有一位上帝
There is only one God.
而他在這裡
And he is here...
與我們同在
with us.
不
No!
摩西
Moses.
Moses!
自由了
Freedom!
朋友們
My friends!
我的…子民
MY... - people.
上帝讓我們擺脫了奴役
God has delivered us from slavery.
我們自由了
We are free.
你們已經歷了漫長的跋涉  我知道
You have come a long way, I know.
但我們的旅途才剛剛開始
But our journey is just beginning.
我們必須相信上帝
We must trust in God.
追隨他的腳步
We must follow his path.
摩西領導以色列人來到了西奈山
Moses leads the Israelites to Mount Sinai...
在這裡  上帝在燃燒的荊棘中第一次與他對話
where God first spoke to him in the burning bush.
上帝將刻在石頭上的法典
God gives laws to Moses...
賜予了摩西
written in stone.
這就是《十誡》
The Ten Commandments.
約書亞
Joshua.
上帝
God has...
重申了他對亞伯拉罕許下的承諾
Renewed the promise he made to Abraham.
我們有了可以在應許之地實行的新法典
We have new laws preparing us for the promised land.
如果我們忠於上帝  他一定會遵守諾言
If we are true to God, he will keep his promise.
亞伯拉罕的夢想
Abraham's dream.
我們的未來
Our future.
你是我們人民的未來  約書亞
You are our people's future, Joshua.
你必須延續上帝對亞伯拉罕所立
You must take the land promised to Abraham...
和他如繁星般多的後裔
and all of his descendants,
所立的約
as numerous as the stars.
下集《聖經》預告
Next time on The Bible.
耶和華帶我們離開了埃及
The Lord brought us out from Egypt.
他承諾將賜予我們這塊土地
He promised us this land.
很快  它就會是我們的了
Soon, it will be ours.
我們必須攻下耶利哥
We must take Jericho.
找一條能讓我進去的路
Just find me a way in.
約書亞
Joshua!
他們知道上帝與我們同在  都陷入恐慌  不戰自潰
The people melt in fear because they know he is with us.
上帝與我們同在
God is with us.
耶和華為摩西將海水分開
The Lord parted the waters for Moses.
而為你  他將讓岩石碎裂
For you, he will split rock.
耶利哥是我們的
Jericho is ours!
如果我們聽從上帝的指引
If we obey the Lord,
一切皆有可能
anything is possible!
以色列
Israel!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
上帝會允你一個兒子
God will give you a son.
你的力量源自上帝
Your strength comes from God.
參孫
Samson,
"你背負著趕走非利士人的使命"
your duty is to drive the Philistines away.
您想讓我怎麼辦
What would you have me do?
拋棄我愛的女人  就因為她是非利士人嗎
Reject the woman I fell in love with just because she's a Philistine?
我們得給以色列人點顏色瞧瞧  我們的女人不是他們可以染指的
We need to send these Israelites a message. They cannot take our women.
為吾妻
For my wife.
你叫什麼名字
What is your name?
我叫大利拉
My name is Delilah.
你為何如此強壯
Why are you so strong?
上帝與我同在  大利拉
God is with me, Delilah.
他賜我神力
He makes me strong.
倘若我剪了頭髮
If I cut my hair,
上帝會收回我的神力
my God will take away all my strength.
你做了什麼
What have you done!
每個人都有自己的價碼
Everyone has their price.
你的上帝拋棄了你
Your God has deserted you...
收回了你的神力
and taken your strength with him.
不  他要我徹底毀了你們
No. He wants me to destroy you all!